南极洲  阿特卡湾的秋天
Autumn in Atka Bay, Antarctica.
几周前  这里还是一片海阔天空
Just a few weeks ago, this was open sea.
如今  正在形成冰封雪盖的新景象
Now, a new frozen landscape is forming.
毫无生机的新世界出现了
This new world appears devoid of life.
也并不是全无生机
Well, almost.
一只皇帝企鹅
An emperor penguin.
它并非孑然一身
And he is not alone.
数千只帝企鹅正向这处冰冻的海湾汇集
Thousands of emperors are coming to this frozen bay.
新结成的冰层
They are here because the new ice
为它们提供了最安全的繁殖地
provides the safest place for them to breed.
冰层会保持冰封九个月
The ice will last nine months,
直到夏季来临时融化
before melting away next summer.
它们将利用这九个月中的每一天
And they will need every day of those nine months
来抚育伟大帝企鹅王朝的后代
to raise the next generation of this great emperor dynasty.
但要做到这一点
But to do so,
它们必须熬过即将来临的冬季
they will have to survive the coming winter.
地球上最冷  最残酷的
The coldest and the cruellest
冬季
on earth.
帝企鹅每年都会重新择偶
Emperors pair up anew every year...
尽管冬季即将来临
And although winter is fast approaching,
寻找完美伴侣的过程
the process of finding the perfect partner
却不能操之过急
cannot be hurried.
新结成的企鹅夫妻会进行优雅的仪式
New couples perform a graceful ritual
来巩固对彼此的承诺
that will cement their commitment to each other.
保持动作同步
Moving together in synchrony
是建立有力情感纽带的关键
is the key to creating a powerful bond.
这必须成为自然界中最牢固的纽带之一
And this bond needs to be one of the strongest in nature...
因为这里每个家庭的存亡
Because the survival of every family here,
以及整个王朝的延续
and therefore the survival of this dynasty,
都取决于这一纽带
depends upon it.
企鹅的身体构造使其能完美应对很多事
A penguin is beautifully designed for many things...
但交配却不是其中之一
But mating is not one of them.
遗憾的是  不是所有企鹅
Unfortunately, not all the penguins
都能找到完美的伴侣
have been able to find the perfect partner.
随着时光飞逝
And, with time fast running out,
这只雌性企鹅不再遵守礼仪
this female forgoes the formalities.
但这对企鹅已经形成坚固的纽带
But this couple has already bonded too tightly
第三者无法将它们拆散
to be split apart by an interloper.
找不到伴侣的企鹅
Penguins unlucky in love
会折回大海觅食  度过这个冬季
head back to spend the winter feeding at sea,
因为冰层上没有食物
because there's no food out here on the ice.
企鹅蛋发育期间
The couples now face weeks of waiting
企鹅夫妻们必须等待数周
while their eggs develop.
但这对企鹅似乎进度超前
But one pair appears to have got ahead of schedule.
企鹅腹部凸起一块
A bulge on a penguin's belly
一般是父母一方把蛋放在脚上保暖的迹象
is normally the sign of a parent keeping an egg warm on its feet.
但它看起来像在
But she seems to be trying to keep
给一个雪球保暖
a snowball warm.
看来它们在为照顾真的企鹅蛋做练习
They appear to be getting in some practice for the real thing.
白昼越来越短  也越来越冷
The days are becoming shorter and colder...
终于
Until finally,
太阳最后一次落下  两个月的极夜开始
the sun sets for the last time for two months.
春季来临前太阳都不会升起
It won't rise again until the spring.
在南极洲的月光下
Now, they live in a twilight world,
它们生活在暮色之中
under the bright Antarctic moon.
对于这对企鹅  漫长的等待即将结束
For this couple, the long wait for their egg is almost over.
企鹅妈妈感觉到了
The female senses it.
它的宫缩开始了
Her contractions have begun.
下一代帝企鹅即将诞生
The next generation of emperors is on its way.
育成一枚企鹅蛋需要大量的能量
Producing an egg takes a huge amount of energy,
企鹅妈妈们要消耗四分之一的体重
such that the females lose a quarter of their body weight.
它已经一个多月没有进食
She hasn't eaten for over a month
需要回到大海中去觅食
and needs to return to the ocean to feed.
它不能带着宝贝企鹅蛋一起去
She can't take her precious egg with her,
必须将它交给伴侣来照顾
so she must pass it to her partner to care for.
企鹅爸爸有一个贴近皮肤的特殊育儿袋
He has a special brood pouch to keep it warm,
来为企鹅蛋保暖
close to his skin.
如果它不能迅速让蛋离开冰面
If he doesn't get the egg off the ice quickly,
蛋就会冻住
it will freeze.
现在它可以离开了
Now, she is free to go.
但它看起来有些不舍
But she does seem rather reluctant to leave.
现在它将在漫长的严冬中
He will now have sole responsibility for their egg
独自照顾它们的蛋
all through the long, harsh winter.
在蛋孵化前
He won't see his partner again
它的伴侣不会回来
until the egg has hatched.
接下来几天  群落中所有的企鹅妈妈
Over the next few days, every female in the colony
都按原路疾行二十四千米
hurries away on the same 15-mile march
到达海边
to the sea.
寒风从大陆中心吹来
A freezing wind blowing in from the heart of the continent
气温急剧下降
drives the temperature down.
为了给自己和企鹅蛋保暖
To keep themselves and their eggs warm,
企鹅爸爸们展现出自然界中
the males now perform one of the most spectacular
最壮观的合作场面之一
demonstrations of cooperation in nature.
一只接一只
One by one,
它们紧紧地挤成一团
they lock themselves into a huddle...
四千多只企鹅爸爸
Creating a giant incubator
组成一个巨大的孵化器
made up of over 4,000 male penguins.
每一只都不断尝试挤进最佳位置
Each individual constantly tries to push into the best possible position
为自己和企鹅蛋保暖
to keep himself and his egg warm.
于是
As a result,
整群企鹅一直保持动态
the entire huddle is forever on the move.
风暴级强风
Storm force winds
使温度下降到零下六十摄氏度
now drive the temperature down to -60 Celsius.
对外层承受寒风的
For the emperors on the outside,
帝企鹅来说
facing the wind,
气候条件变得难以忍受
the conditions become unbearable.
它们别无选择  只能脱离群体
They have no choice but to break off
尝试绕到有掩蔽的一侧去
and try to get round to the sheltered side.
它必须站起来
He must get back on his feet,
但不能让企鹅蛋滑出来
but without letting go of his egg.
如果失败  蛋中的胚胎
If he fails, the embryo inside
会很快冻住  然后死去
will rapidly freeze and die.
绕到有掩蔽的一侧后
Once they arrive on the sheltered side of the huddle,
它们得以从寒风中稍作喘息
they get some relief from the wind.
这里的暴风雪
When a blizzard sets in here,
会连续肆虐数天
it rages for days on end.
现在  伤亡显露出来
Now, the casualties are revealed.
伤痕累累  饥寒交迫  精疲力竭
Battered, starving and exhausted,
这些生还者仍不能放松
there is still no relief for the survivors.
暴风雪使他们将近移动两千米
The storm has driven them nearly a mile
偏离了最安全的冰上通道
from the safest path of the ice.
返回原来的位置是一趟疲惫的旅程
It's a weary march back to where they started from.
现在  它们又重新挤成一团
Now, they re-form their huddle,
准备对抗下一场暴风雪
to be ready for the next storm...
暴风雪必然会再次来临
..Which will come, inevitably.
两个月的恶劣气候之后
Only after two months of brutal weather
极夜终于结束了
does the polar night finally come to an end.
随之而来的是一丝暖意
And with it comes a hint of warmth.
太阳的回归正与
The return of the sun coincides
群落中新成员的诞生同步
with the appearance of the newest members of the colony.
几天之内就将新增几千张
In a matter of days, there are thousands
饥饿的嘴  嗷嗷待哺
of hungry mouths, all demanding food.
它们的爸爸们已将近四个月没有进食
Their fathers haven't eaten anything for nearly four months.
不过它们保存了重要储备
Yet they have kept back a vital reserve,
一种浓浓的企鹅奶
a kind of thick penguin milk,
专为此刻准备
just for this moment.
但是这只能让企鹅宝宝存活几天
But it's only enough to keep the chick alive for a few days.
企鹅妈妈们必须尽快带着食物回来
The females must return soon with food.
对一些宝宝来说  已经来不及了
For some, it's already too late.
第一批企鹅妈妈们正在回来的路上
The first of the females are returning.
丰腴饱足  越来越多
Fat and well fed, more arrive,
都带着给企鹅宝宝的食物
all with food for the chicks.
企鹅爸爸们已迫不及待
And not a moment too soon for the waiting fathers.
企鹅妈妈第一次见到自己的宝宝
A mother's first sight of her young chick.
重新确认纽带后
With their bond reaffirmed,
企鹅一家开始庆祝
the whole family celebrates.
终于  企鹅爸爸可以
Now at last, he can hand over
将宝贝小企鹅交给妈妈了
his precious chick to its mother.
但是也有些企鹅妈妈遭受不幸
But there are less fortunate females here,
它们的宝宝死了
whose chicks have died.
可是它们的育儿本能仍然很强烈
Yet their parenting instinct is still strong.
移交企鹅宝宝的这一幕
The sight of a youngster being handed over
让它们难以抗拒
is irresistible.
更多失去宝宝的企鹅妈妈加入混战
More chickless females join in the melee.
企鹅宝宝看起来很安全
The chick appears to be safe...
但是它离开了亲生父母
But it is no longer with its true parents.
被绑架的小企鹅从来不会有好下场
The prospects for a kidnapped chick are never good.
尽管这对企鹅过去三个月付出了巨大努力
Despite their immense efforts over the last three months,
它们的努力没有施展的对象
this couple have nothing to show for it.
对那些成功的父母来说
For those couples that have been successful,
现在轮到企鹅爸爸回到海中去
it's the father's turn to head back to sea
它们迫切需要饱餐一顿
to get a much-needed meal for himself...
并承担为它们的宝宝觅食的责任
..And to take his turn collecting food for the chick.
企鹅妈妈现在可以和刚出世的宝宝
The mother is now able to bond
建立纽带
with her new baby...
更紧急的是  喂养宝宝
..And, urgently, to feed it.
这是它第一次尝到海产
Its first taste of sea food.
但苦难还未结束
But the times of hardship are not over.
又一场暴风雪
Another storm,
又一场雪茫
and another white-out.
对一些企鹅来说  这是一场灾难
For some, this is a catastrophe.
它们跌入了冰上的一处深沟
They have tumbled into a ravine in the ice...
四周都是陡峭光滑的冰墙
..With steep, slippery walls.
企鹅宝宝现在成了致命的累赘
Chicks are now a deadly burden.
带着宝宝的妈妈无法攀冰
Mothers carrying young cannot grip the ice.
如果妈妈出不去
If she doesn't get out,
它们都会死
they will both die.
这只企鹅妈妈不得不做出可怕的抉择
This mother has had to make a terrible choice.
为了自救
To save herself,
它抛弃了自己的宝宝
she has abandoned her chick.
至少  有一只企鹅妈妈不打算放弃它的宝宝
One mother, at least, is not prepared to give up on her chick.
妈妈和宝宝都安全了
Mother and chick are safe.
偶尔
There is, occasionally,
南极洲的无情也会暂息
a respite from the brutality of Antarctica.
天空晴朗  微风吹拂
Clear skies, gentle winds...
一场尤为壮观的南极光
..And a particularly spectacular display of the Southern Lights.
南极光
The Aurora Australis.
随着太阳越攀越高
As the sun climbs higher every day,
冰层转暖
it warms the ice.
很快  帝企鹅的冰封世界
Soon, the emperors' frozen world
将开始融化
will start to melt away.
在过去的几周里
For the last few weeks,
企鹅妈妈和爸爸
the mother and father have
轮流喂养它们的宝宝
taken it in turn to feed their offspring.
但很快  它日渐增长的胃口将迫使它的父母
But its growing appetite will soon force both parents to go away
同时出海捕鱼
fishing at the same time.
是时候鼓励满月的小企鹅
Now it's time to encourage the month-old chicks
用自己的双脚站立
to stand on their own two feet.
有时  父母需要适时把它们踢开
Sometimes, it takes a well-timed kick.
现在  父母都可以出海捕鱼了
Now, both parents can head off to sea to go fishing.
有生以来第一次
For the first time,
企鹅宝宝们要脱离父母的保护
the chicks will have to face the elements
独自面对自然了
without a parent to protect them.
其余成年企鹅并不会照料它们
Other adults certainly won't look after them.
于是孤单的企鹅宝宝聚在一起以求安慰
So, lone chicks gather together for comfort.
当温度降至零下二十五摄氏度时
As the temperature drops to -25,
企鹅宝宝们本能地挤作一团
the chicks instinctively create their own mini-huddle,
就像它们的爸爸一样
just as their fathers do.
此时此刻
This is no time
小企鹅万万不可脱离群体
for a youngster to be alone.
幸运的企鹅宝宝
If they're lucky,
此时或许仍有
some chicks may still have
捕鱼归来的父母保护
the protection of a parent taking a break from fishing.
但对于大多数幼崽来说
But for the majority,
紧抱成团给了它们仅有的庇护
the huddle is their only shelter.
即便天气恶劣  成年企鹅仍需
Even in this weather, adults must still
多次出海带回食物
head back and forth to the sea to bring back food.
幼崽跟随成年企鹅的本能依旧强烈
The instinct to follow adults is still strong.
但在暴风雪之中
But in a blizzard,
这种做法并不明智
that is a bad idea.
成年企鹅的离去
The adults' disappearance
让企鹅宝宝们困惑不已
leaves the chicks in confusion.
它迷茫而孤独  唯一的希望是
Lost and alone, his only hope
这只成年企鹅正在返回群落
is that this adult is heading back to the colony,
而非在冰冻废原上越走越远
and not away from it, across the frozen wastes.
最后一场风暴结束后
With the last of the big storms over,
夏天到来了
summer has arrived.
企鹅聚居的冰层开始消融
The ice that has been the penguins' home is melting.
企鹅宝宝们几乎发育完全
These chicks are almost fully grown,
即将独立
and approaching independence.
在它们下海之前  所有帝企鹅
Before they leave for the sea, all emperors -
不分长幼  都需要换毛
adults and their chicks, must moult.
对于小企鹅来说  这意味着它们步入了成年
For the youngsters, this marks the arrival of adulthood.
三分之二的幼崽历经磨难  得以生存
Against all the odds, two thirds have survived.
但逐年缩减的冰雪世界
But the annual disappearance of their ice world
正是企鹅命运未卜的警示
is a reminder that they face an uncertain future.
海洋温度年复一年地增加
Ocean temperatures are expected to rise year-on-year.
帝企鹅赖以生存的南极海冰
This Antarctic sea ice on which all emperor penguins rely
或许会过早融化
may not freeze for long enough each year
使它们来不及完成非凡的生命周期
for them to complete their extraordinary life cycle.
当整个群落准备离开阿特卡湾时
But, as the whole colony prepares to leave Atka Bay...
这些企鹅父母成功养育了
These parents have successfully raised
帝企鹅王朝的下一代
the next generation in this emperors' dynasty.